{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "A painting by this man was ordered defaced by the Council of Trent, leading to the man who\naltered his work being known as \"The Breeches-Painter.\" Daniele da Volterra added loincloths to\ncover the nudity in this man's The Last Judgment. For 10 points, name this painter who worked\nlying on his back on a scaffold to decorate the ceiling of the Sistine Chapel.",
      "answer": [
        "Michelangelo",
        "Michelangelo di Lodovico Buonarroti Simoni",
        "Buonarroti"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer was patronized by Cardinal Rudolf of Austria, to whom he dedicated his\nArchduke Trio. This composer wrapped his head in pillows and hid in a basement during the\nBattle of Wagram, attempting to protect what little hearing he had left. For 10 points, name this\ncomposer of the Pastoral and Choral symphonies as well as \"Fur Elise.\"",
      "answer": [
        "Ludwig van Beethoven",
        "Beethoven"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Neil Armstrong took a recording of theramin music and this man’s ninth symphony on Apollo 11. He\nwrote his twelfth string quartet while spending a summer in Spillville, Iowa, though his Slavonic Dances\nhonored Brahms and paid tribute to his native Bohemia. For ten points, name this Czech composer who,\nwhile visiting America, wrote his Symphony no. 9, “From the New World.”",
      "answer": [
        "Antonin Dvorak",
        "Dvorak"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "With Fred Archer, this artist gave pure white a value of ten in the Zone System. He showed\nJapanese-Americans at Manzanar in his work Born Free and Equal, and with Willard Van Dyke and\nEdward Weston, he formed the group f/64. This artist captured images of El Capitan and a round granite\nformation in Yosemite National Park. For ten points, name this photographer of Moon and Half Dome.",
      "answer": [
        "Ansel Easton Adams",
        "Adams"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 2003, a copy of this painting was covered by a blue curtain while Colin Powell addressed the United\nNations. On the left side of this painting, a bull stands over a woman who is holding her dead child. An\neye-shaped light bulb explodes in this painting above an impaled, screaming horse. For ten points, name\nthis painting inspired by the bombing of the title Basque town, a massive painting by Pablo Picasso.",
      "answer": "Guernica"
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer popularized a percussion-heavy style music inspired by Janissary bands with an opera\nin which Belmonte rescues Konstanze from Pasha Selim’s harem. He included heavy Masonic symbolism\nin an opera in which Tamino overcomes a series of trials with the help of the title woodwind. For ten\npoints, name this composer of The Abduction From The Seraglio and The Magic Flute.",
      "answer": [
        "Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart",
        "Mozart"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This building’s gate includes the inscription “O Soul, thou art at rest” from the 89th sura of the\nQuran. It lies on the south bank of the Yamuna River, north of a garden with a pool reflecting this\nbuilding’s image. Its design includes four minarets, four small domes, and a large primary dome, and\nit was built as a tomb for Mumtaz, the emperor’s wife. Shah Jahan built, for ten points, what Muslim\nmausoleum in Agra, a masterpiece of Indian architecture?",
      "answer": "Taj Mahal"
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer wrote the twelve-tone Connotations for the opening of Lincoln Center. He quoted\n“Camptown Races” in a composition that features a narrator reciting the Gettysburg Address. He\ndepicted a couple in western Pennsylvania in a ballet choreographed by Martha Graham that incorporates\nthe Shaker hymn “Simple Gifts.” For ten points, name this American composer of Lincoln Portrait and\nAppalachian Spring.",
      "answer": [
        "Aaron Copland",
        "Copland"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer’s overture to Rienzi was performed at every Nuremburg Rally. This man attacked\nFelix Mendelssohn in the anti-Semitic tract On Jewishness in Music. He used the term “music dramas” to\ndescribe his operas. King Ludwig II’s castle Neuschwanstein [noysh-vahn-stein] was inspired by the operas\nof this man, which are often performed at his opera house in Bayreuth [bye-royt]. For ten points, name\nthis German composer of Lohengrin and The Ring Cycle.",
      "answer": [
        "Richard Wagner",
        "Wagner"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This artist showed three women crying as three brothers raise their arms toward swords in one work based on Roman legend. This Neoclassicist painter later depicted Napoleon with a hand tucked in his clothes in his study at the Tuileries [too-leh-ree], and on a rearing horse crossing the Alps. The subject of one of this artist’s works lies slumped over a desk in his bathtub after being stabbed by Charlotte Corday. For ten points, identify the French painter of The Oath of the Horatii and The Death of Marat.",
      "answer": [
        "Jacques-Louis David",
        "David"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This artistic medium was historically manufactured on the island of Murano in Venice. Dale Chihuly\nprimarily works in this medium, which was used to create four pyramids for the courtyard of the Louvre\nby I.M. Pei. A colored type of this medium was used by Louis Comfort Tiffany for a series of ornate\nlamps, as well as in the windows of Chartres Cathedral. For ten points, identify this sand-based artistic\nmedium, often used in “stained” windows.",
      "answer": [
        "glass",
        "brown glass",
        "stained glass"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This material was used for the Capitoline Museum’s sculpture of a she-wolf with the infant Romulus\nand Remus. Sculptures in this artistic medium were often made using the lost-wax method. An artist used\nthis material for a circle of six men about to be executed during the Hundred Years War, known as The\nBurghers of Calais, and for a nude sculpture claimed to be cast from a living model. For ten points, name\nthis metal used by Auguste Rodin [roh-dan] to create The Thinker and a sculpture of its Age.",
      "answer": [
        "bronze",
        "The Age of Bronze"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Philip the Good ordered the construction of one of these objects called Mons Meg. An early metal\nversion of these objects was called the pot-de-fer, and culverins were portable types of these items. The\nHungarian engineer Orban designed a massive one of these objects that malfunctioned and killed him.\nVauban designed star forts to defend against these weapons, which Mehmed II used to destroy the walls\nof Constantinople in 1453. For ten points, name these gunpowder-based artillery pieces.",
      "answer": [
        "cannons",
        "bombards"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This artist sculpted the facade of a memorial for Julius II, including a seated sculpture of Moses\nwith small horns. A sculpture of a Biblical hero by this artist was originally commissioned for the Duomo\nCathedral and lacks both a sword and the severed head of a giant, unlike a similar work by Donatello. For\nten points, name this Italian artist of a nude marble David and the ceiling frescos of the Sistine Chapel.",
      "answer": [
        "Michelangelo Buonarroti",
        "Michelangelo",
        "Buonarroti"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer quoted “Come, my dearest, why so sad this morning,” in a piece written to benefit wounded Serbian soldiers in 1876. This composer celebrated Romanov imperialism with the polonaise that ends his Symphony no. 3, “Polish.” This composer of the Marche Slave used “La Marseillaise” to represent Napoleon’s invading army in an overture that, when played in the US, often accompanies fireworks. For ten points, name this Russian composer who included cannons in his 1812 Overture.",
      "answer": "Pyotr Ilyich Tchaikovsky"
    },
    {
      "question": "A blindfolded man is tied to a post in a print by this artist titled “Nothing To Be Done,” part of a series called The Disasters of War that shows violent scenes from the Peninsular War. This artist’s painting of Mameluke horsemen in the Puerta del Sol is set one day before another of his works that shows a firing squad aiming at a man in a white shirt outside of Madrid. For ten points, name this Spanish painter of The Third of May, 1808.",
      "answer": "Francisco Goya y Lucientes"
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer protested in support of Alfred Dreyfus by refusing to perform in Paris in 1899. He included an “Arietta” and a tribute to Niels Gade in a ten-book set of 66 short piano pieces, and a tympani roll opens his only Piano Concerto, in A minor. This composer of the Lyric Pieces also wrote incidental music for a Henrik Ibsen play that includes “Anitra’s Dance” and “Morning Mood.” For ten points, name this nationalist Norwegian composer who wrote Peer Gynt.",
      "answer": "Edvard Grieg"
    },
    {
      "question": "This painting’s date and the artist’s name are depicted on a handkerchief held by a boy. Two figures on either side of this painting’s title figure are depicted in golden robes. This painting is noted for its distinct “heaven” and “earth” sections, the latter of which depicts Saint Stephen and Saint Augustine descending for the title event. For ten points, name this El Greco painting showing the interment of the title nobleman.",
      "answer": [
        "The Burial of the Count of Orgaz",
        "El Entierro del Senor de Orgaz"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This city’s tallest commercial building is One Franklin Square, which was granted an exemption to the 1910 Height of Buildings Act and reaches 210 feet. In 2017, stained glass windows commemorating Robert E. Lee and Stonewall Jackson were removed from this city’s third tallest building, the National Cathedral. For ten points, name this city where every building is at least 200 feet shorter than a 555-foot monument to the first President of the United States.",
      "answer": [
        "Washington D.C.",
        "DC",
        "District of Columbia"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A sculpture of this man “Enthroned” was created by Horatio Greenough in the style of Zeus of Olympia. This man was depicted with Commerce, Science, Mechanics, and 13 maidens in his Apotheosis by Constantino Brumidi. This man is the central figure in Grant Wood’s Daughters of the Revolution, and he was depicted in Wood’s painting of Parson Weems’ Fable cutting down a cherry tree. For ten points, name this leader who was depicted crossing the Delaware River.",
      "answer": "George Washington"
    },
    {
      "question": "An article in the New York Tribune informed the composer of this piece that he was busy working on it, a complete surprise to him. This piece, which premiered at New York City’s Aeolian Hall on Abraham Lincoln’s birthday in 1924 with its composer on the piano, opens with a glissando on the clarinet. For ten points, name this fusion of classical music and jazz, a musical piece by George Gershwin.",
      "answer": "Rhapsody in Blue"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1908, Joseph Szombathy discovered a faceless depiction of this figure in the village of Willendorf. A Velazquez painting of this figure looking back at herself in a mirror was attacked by suffragette Mary Richardson. In another painting, this figure is blown by Zephyrus to shore and stands on a giant shell. An armless statue discovered on the island of Milos depicts, for ten points, what goddess whose birth is depicted in a painting by Sandro Botticelli?",
      "answer": [
        "Venus",
        "Aphrodite",
        "Venus of Willendorf, Rokeby Venus, Venus de Milo, and/or Birth of Venus"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader initiated a series of economic reforms as part of Operation Forward. A mass sterilization campaign was carried out by this leader during the 21-month long Emergency. The Smiling Buddha test was authorized by this leader who ordered a raid on the Golden Temple in Amritsar in Operation Blue Star. Two Sikh bodyguards assassinated, for ten points, what Indian Prime Minister, the daughter of Jawaharlal Nehru?",
      "answer": "Indira Gandhi"
    },
    {
      "question": "One example of this musical form was inspired by a cat walking on a harpsichord and was composed by Domenico Scarlatti. Fourteen of these pieces in D minor are labeled “Contrapunctus” in a work titled for The Art of [these pieces]. Renaissance music theorist Gioseffo Zarlino contrasted these works and canons in the 16th century. J.S. Bach wrote a D minor organ piece that pairs one of these works with a “Toccata.” For ten points, name this type of contrapuntal work that is often paired with a prelude.",
      "answer": "fugues"
    },
    {
      "question": "John Singer Sargent created a portrait of this man “painting by the edge of a wood” with his wife Alice. This artist, who observed and painted the Rouen Cathedral under several different light conditions, built a garden-filled estate in Giverny [zhi-vair-nee] that is now a museum dedicated to him. Japanese-style bridges and water lilies were popular subjects of paintings by, for ten points, what French painter whose painting of a sunrise gave its name to the Impressionist movement?",
      "answer": "Claude Monet"
    },
    {
      "question": "This piece includes a “shuffle” theme whose melody parallels that of its composer’s song “The Man I Love.” This piece, which was orchestrated by Ferde Grof´e [ferd gro-FAY], called for “vernacular instruments” such as a banjo. The “Train” theme in this piece was inspired by the “steely rhythms” of its composer’s train ride to Boston. This piece, commissioned for “An Experiment in Modern Music” by Paul Whiteman in 1924, begins with a 17-note clarinet glissando. For ten points, name this “jazz concerto” by George Gershwin.",
      "answer": "Rhapsody in Blue"
    },
    {
      "question": "A Velazquez painting of this figure was attacked by suffragette Mary Richardson. A faceless depiction of this figure was discovered in 1908 by Joseph Szombathy in the village of Willendorf. In another painting, this figure is blown to shore by Zephyrus and stands on a giant shell. An armless statue discovered on the island of Milos depicts, for ten points, what goddess whose birth is depicted in a painting by Sandro Botticelli? R",
      "answer": [
        "Venus",
        "Aphrodite",
        "Venus of Willendorf, Rokeby Venus, Venus de Milo,",
        "Birth of Venus"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Girolamo Frescobaldi and Jean Lully Batiste were composers from the early part of this period. This period of music was significant for ushering in the transition from modal to tonal styles, and music from this period tended to be dense and complex, forming a polyphony of voices through arrangements such as the fugue. For ten points, identify this period of music named after the Portuguese word for “misshapen pearl,” lasting from roughly 1600-1750 and including notable composers such as Bach and Handel.",
      "answer": "Baroque T"
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. After this event, its subject gave an object to a maid at a brothel, who promptly fainted. Martin Bailey has suggested this non-fatal action may have occurred after its subject found out his brother Theo was getting married. This event occurred in 1888 after its subject got into an argument with Paul Gauguin at their house in Arles. For ten points, name this event, in which a Dutch painter lost a body part.",
      "answer": [
        "Vincent Van Gogh cutting off his own ear",
        "anything with the words Van Gogh and ear, and something indicating it is being removed T"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Jeremiah Clarke wrote a \"voluntary\" for this instrument often played at weddings. J.S. Bach's second Brandenburg Concerto contains a challenging solo for the \"piccolo\" type of this instrument. Usually pitched in B-flat, this instrument is used to play many fanfares, and has a mellower tone than a cornet. For ten points, name this brass instrument with three valves, commonly used in classical and jazz music.",
      "answer": "Trumpet"
    },
    {
      "question": "Johann Peter Salomon gave this man’s 41st and final symphony the nickname Jupiter. This resident of Salzburg wrote a set of variations on a French folk song, later combined with words as “Twinkle, Twinkle, Little Star.” According to legend, this man left his Requiem unfinished because he was poisoned by Antonio Salieri. The composer of A Little Night Music and the opera The Magic Flute, for ten points, F name this 18th-century Austrian composer and child prodigy.",
      "answer": "Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart"
    },
    {
      "question": "One building in this city was designed by James Hoban and contains the Blue Room. This city’s streets were mapped out by Charles L’Enfant [lahn-FAHN], and it is home to a Maya Lin-designed wall with the names of casualties of the Vietnam War. In this city, the National Mall contains the Air and Space Museum and many other buildings owned by the Smithsonian Institution. For ten points, name A this city whose famous works of architecture include the U.S. Capitol and the White House.",
      "answer": [
        "Washington, D.C.",
        "D.C.",
        "District of Columbia"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The building of this structure was supervised by Ustad Ahmad Lahauri, who also laid the foundations of the Red Fort. This building, whose name is derived from Persian, was ordered by an emperor who was put under house arrest by his successor, Aurangzeb [[ow- RAHNG-zeb]]. This building was originally constructed to house the tomb of Mumtaz. For ten points, name this enormous mausoleum in Agra, India, constructed by Shah Jahan.",
      "answer": "Taj Mahal"
    },
    {
      "question": "Verrocchio [[veh-ROH-kyoh]] depicted this figure in bronze following his most famous action, while Bernini sculpted a marble statue of this man during that same violent action. Donatello's sculpture of this figure was the first freestanding nude since antiquity, and another depiction of this hero has an oversized head to appear proportional from below. For ten points, name this Biblical king who was depicted in a marble sculpture by Michelangelo before he slays Goliath.",
      "answer": [
        "David or Davit",
        "Daud"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "At this event, a preacher became famous for saying \"Praise the Lord and pass the ammunition\" to rally the spirit of the troops. This attack, codenamed Operation Z, began after one side exclaimed, \"Tora! Tora! Tora!\" This event resulted in the deaths of over 2,000 servicemen, primarily due to the sinking of both the USS Oklahoma and the USS Arizona. For ten points, name this attack on December 7th, 1941, in which Japan bombed a U.S. naval base in Hawaii.",
      "answer": [
        "Attack on Pearl Harbor",
        "equivalents mentioning Pearl Harbor",
        "Operation Z before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The story of this opera was adapted for a 1998 musical of the same name with music by Elton John. An original \"potpourri\" overture was written for this opera, though it was cut from the 1871 premiere in Cairo. At the end of this opera, the title Ethiopian princess dies in the arms of her lover Radamès [[rah-dah-MESS]], while priests sing hymns to Ptah. For ten points, name this four-act opera by Giuseppe Verdi about a romantic tragedy in the Old Kingdom of Egypt.",
      "answer": "Aida"
    },
    {
      "question": "This artist may depict Harman van Swole in a Portrait of a Slav Prince later bought by Catherine the Great. This artist was hired by the Guild ofSurgeonsinhishomenationto paint the dissection ofthedeceasedcriminalArisKindt.Anotherworkbythismandepictsa shooting company led by FranzBanningCocq[[\"COKE\"]]inTheNightWatch.Fortenpoints, name this prolific Dutch artist whose other work includes many self-portraits and The Anatomy Lesson of Dr. Nicolaes Tulp. ANSWER:Rembrandtvan Rijn(orRembrandtHarmenszoonvan Rijn; accept either underlined portion) (2) Medal of Honor-winner Bud Day saved this man'slifeafterhedroppedathirdofhis body weight while in the Vietnamese POW camp called \"The Plantation.\" With Russ Feingold, this senator names a campaign reform bill which limits the amount of \"soft money\" available to candidates. This politician succeeded Barry Goldwater as senatorfrom Arizona in 1987. The 2008 Republican candidateforU.S.presidentwas,fortenpoints,what politician who died in 2018?",
      "answer": "JohnMcCainor John SidneyMcCainIII"
    },
    {
      "question": "Josephus[[joh-SEE-fus]]claimedthismonarchledafutilethirteen-yearsiegeofTyre [[\"TIRE\"]], later coming to terms with its king, Ithobaal III [[ith-oh-BALE \"the third\"]]. This restorer of the Ishtar Gate supposedly blinded the king of Judah, Zedekiah, for rebelling against his rule. In the biblical tradition, this Chaldean [[kahl-DEE-un]] king cast Shadrach [[SHAD-rak]], Meshach [[MEE-shak]], and Abednego [[ah-BED-neh-go]] into the fiery furnace and had his dreams interpreted by Daniel. For ten points, name this long-reigning king of the Neo-Babylonian Empire. ANSWER:Nebuchadnezzar[[neh-buh-kahd-NEH-zar]] II(orNabû-kudurri-uṣur; accept Nebuchadnezzarthe Great) (7) In this city's Congress of Peace, it was determined that the Holy See shouldhaveits sovereignty revoked. The League of Nations headquarters was moved from London to this neutral city in 1920, remaining so until the League's dissolution. French reformer John Calvin led a semi-theocratic government in this city during the 16th century. A convention that regulates the rules of war is named for, for ten points, what Swiss city? ANSWER:Geneva(acceptGenève; orGenf; orGinevra) (8) While head of the Provisional Theatre, Bedřich Smetana [[BED-ur-zhik SMEH-tah-nah]] returned this composer's first draft of the historical comedy King and Charcoal Burner after declaring it unperformable. His time in Iowa among fellow Central Europeans led to this composer writing the American Quartet. African-American spirituals influenced this man's composition, Symphony from the New World. Bohemian folk music often inspired, for ten points, which Czech composer'sSlavonic Dances?",
      "answer": "AntonínDvořák] or AntonínLeopoldDvořák 2021-22 C Set History"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This artist depicted Nazi concentration camp victims in The Charnel House. In the late 1940s,\nthis wealthy artist was the primary financial backer of the French Communist Party. An earlier\npolitical painting by him shows a lightbulb, a horse, and a screaming woman in memory of a\nBasque village bombed by the Nazis. For 10 points, name this creator of Guernica.",
        "answer": "Pablo Picasso, Picasso, Pablo Ruiz y Picasso"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "World War II itself caused the disappearance of many artworks, such as the Amber\nRoom formerly found in what city, which was besieged by Nazis for nine hundred days?",
        "answer": "St. Petersburg, Leningrad"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s government organized the Congress of People’s Deputies and signed the\nIntermediate-Range Nuclear Forces Treaty. He introduced economic restructuring known as\n\"perestroika\" (pr. peh-rez-TROY-kuh) and government transparency called \"glasnost\". For 10\npoints, name this rival of Boris Yeltsin who was the final leader of the Soviet Union.",
        "answer": [
          "Mikhail Gorbachev",
          "Gorbachev",
          "Mikhail Sergeyevich Gorbachev"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Gorbachev ended the \"internal exile\" of what dissenting physicist, the inventor of the\nSoviet hydrogen bomb and namesake of a human rights prize?",
        "answer": [
          "Andrei Sakharov",
          "Sakharov",
          "Andrei Dmitrievich Sakharov"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This composer incorporated \"Springfield Mountain\" and \"Camptown Races,\" along with\nexcerpts from the Gettysburg Address, into his World War II patriotic piece A Lincoln Portrait.\nHe scored ballets about Billy the Kid and about pioneers building a farmhouse in western\nPennsylvania. For 10 points, name this composer of Appalachian Spring.",
        "answer": [
          "Aaron Copland",
          "Copland"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "As part of the same biographical project that led Copland to create A Lincoln Portrait,\nVirgil Thomson set poems by what author of Leaves of Grass?",
        "answer": [
          "Walt Whitman",
          "Whitman",
          "Walter Whitman"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Shortly after his death, this man was nominated for an Oscar for his work on Shall We Dance,\nfor which he wrote the song \"They Can't Take That Away From Me\" with his brother Ira. This\ncomposer used traffic horns in the score to An American in Paris and rumbas in his Cuban\nOverture. For 10 points, name this composer of the jazz concerto Rhapsody in Blue.",
        "answer": [
          "George Gershwin",
          "Gershwin"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Gershwin adapted a play by DuBose Heyward into what opera, which has been both\npraised and criticized for its portrayal of black South Carolinians on Catfish Row?",
        "answer": "Porgy and Bess"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was approached by Thomas Edison's agent Theo Wangemann in 1889, leading him\nto make the first-ever audio recording by a leading composer. This composer relied on Martin\nLuther's translation of the Bible as the text for his German Requiem. For 10 points, name this\ncomposer whom Hans von Bulow first grouped with Beethoven and Bach as the \"Three Bs.\"",
        "answer": [
          "Johannes Brahms",
          "Brahms"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Brahms was born in what city, now the second largest city by population of Germany\nand once a major center of the Hanseatic League?",
        "answer": "Hamburg"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this event, paratroopers captured bridges on the River Orne and Saint-Mere-Eglise. The First \nUS Army Group participated in Operation Quicksilver prior to this campaign, and was commanded by\nGeneral Patton. The Canadians were supposed to capture Caen during this operation, and the Americans\nwere assigned to Fortress Cherbourg, part of the Atlantic Wall. For ten points, name this operation, an\nAllied landing on five beaches in Northern France.",
        "answer": [
          "Operation Overlord",
          "Overlord",
          "D-Day",
          "Battle of Normandy",
          "Normandy"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Operation Dragoon, landings after Operation Overlord in the south of France, targeted Toulon\nand this other Mediterranean port, now the second largest French city.",
        "answer": "Marseilles"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of these people is the title character of an opera which was revised to add a “Polish act” and ends\nwith the Holy Fool lamenting his country’s fate in Kromy Forest. In another opera, Ivan Susanin sacrifices\nhimself for this title leader. The lead-up to the Time of Troubles was chronicled in Modest Mussorgsky’s\nopera about one of these monarchs, Boris Godunov. For ten points, Mikhail Glinka wrote an opera about\nA Life For what leaders of the Russian Empire?",
        "answer": [
          "tsars"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Nikolai Rimsky-Korsakov’s opera The Tale of Tsar Saltan is best known for what virtuosic\norchestral excerpt in which the Tsar’s son is changed into an insect?",
        "answer": "Flight of the Bumblebee"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This composer wrote a piece originally intended for a “mechanical orchestra” to commemorate the\nBattle of Vitoria, Wellington’s Victory. He included a funeral march in a symphony which was dedicated\n“to the memory of a great man” after its original dedicatee, Napoleon Bonaparte, declared himself\nEmperor. This finale of this man’s last symphony was a setting of a Friedrich Schiller poem. For ten\npoints, name this composer of the Eroica Symphony whose Symphony #9 includes the “Ode to Joy.”",
        "answer": [
          "Ludwig van Beethoven",
          "Beethoven"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which five-movement symphony of Beethoven’s was subtitled “Recollections of Country Life”\nand included a musical depiction of a thunderstorm?",
        "answer": [
          "Pastoral Symphony",
          "Pastoral",
          "Symphony no. 6 in F Major",
          "6"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This composer wrote a piece for the funeral of the Electress of Saxony Christiane Eberhardine known\nas the Trauerode. He wrote a piece to cure Count Kaiserling’s insomnia; that piece consists of an aria and\nthirty variations and was twice recorded by Glenn Gould. A collection of preludes and fugues in every\nmajor and minor key was composed by, for ten points, what Baroque composer of the Goldberg Variations\nand the Well-Tempered Clavier?",
        "answer": [
          "Johann Sebastian Bach",
          "Bach"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Bach wrote this set of six orchestral works in an effort to gain employment with the margrave\nChristian Ludwig. Bach is believed to have played the harpsichord himself at the premiere of the fifth of\nthese works,",
        "answer": "Brandenburg Concertos"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Many composers in this country were accused of “formalism” in the Zhdanov Doctrine. A composer\nhere withdrew his Mahler-inspired Fourth Symphony after the editorial “Muddle Instead of Music”\nattacked his modernist opera Lady Macbeth of the Mtsensk District. Socialist realism was the official\nartistic style of, for ten points, what nation where Dmitry Shostakovich fell out of favor with the\nCommunist Party under Joseph Stalin?",
        "answer": [
          "USSR",
          "Soviet Union",
          "Union of Soviet Socialist Republics"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "“Muddle Instead of Music” was published in what newspaper, the official publication of the\nSoviet Communist Party, whose Russian name translates to “Truth?”",
        "answer": "Pravda"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This artist created a work inspired by Goya’s 3rd of May, 1808 showing pregnant women with children\nin front of a futuristic firing squad; that work was a response to U.S. involvement in the Korean War.\nAnother work by this artist includes a flower growing from a sword held in a severed arm. A screaming\nhorse stands under a light bulb in that monochrome work by this artist. For ten points, name this Cubist\npainter who depicted the bombing of a Basque town during the Spanish Civil War in Guernica.",
        "answer": [
          "Pablo Ruiz y Picasso",
          "Picasso",
          "Pablo Picasso"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Picasso also created a series of etchings, similar in style to Guernica, named for “The Dream\nand Lie” of this Spanish general and leader.",
        "answer": [
          "Francisco Franco Bahamonde",
          "Franco",
          "Francisco Franco"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One work created for this location includes a self-portrait of the artist as the flayed skin of Saint\nBartholomew. Julius II commissioned an artist to decorate part of this location with 12 prophets and\nsibyls, as well as scenes from Genesis. A panel at this location shows a bearded figure surrounded by angels\nas he reaches toward a nude man. Papal conclaves are held in, for ten points, what room of the Apostolic\nPalace, whose artworks include The Last Judgement and The Creation of Adam by Michelangelo?",
        "answer": "Sistine Chapel"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This other artist designed now lost tapestries for the Sistine Chapel, in addition to painting The\nSchool of Athens for the library of Julius II.",
        "answer": [
          "Raphael",
          "Raffaello",
          "Raffaello Sanzio da Urbino"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One piece by this composer depicts the Paris catacombs and a planned monument to celebrate the\nfailure of an assassination attempt on Alexander II. Nikolai Rimsky-Korsakov arranged this man’s music\nfor a tone poem depicting a witches’ Sabbath on St. John’s Eve. The drawings of Viktor Hartmann inspired\na suite by this man that ends with “The Great Gate of Kiev” and includes a recurring Promenade theme.\nFor ten points, name this Russian composer of Night on Bald Mountain and Pictures at an Exhibition.",
        "answer": [
          "Modest Mussorgsky",
          "Mussorgsky"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mussorgsky and Rimsky-Korsakov were both members of what group of nationalist Russian\ncomposers that also included Mily Balakirev, Cesar Cui, and Alexander Borodin?",
        "answer": [
          "The Mighty Handful",
          "The Mighty Five",
          "Five"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A building featuring a coffered one of these structures was originally commissioned by Marcus Agrippa\nand renovated by Hadrian. Constantino Brumidi decorated the interior surface of one of these structures\nwith murals that can be seen from the rotunda below. An oculus allows light to shine into the Pantheon\nthrough, for ten points, what architectural feature that serves as the roof of the United States Capitol\nbuilding?",
        "answer": "domes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The murals in the inside of the Capitol rotunda show the Apotheosis of this leader, who was\nalso shown being crowned by fame and peace in a relief sculpture on an exterior wall.",
        "answer": [
          "George Washington",
          "Washington"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This composer’s exposure to gamelan at the 1889 World’s Fair inspired his Estampes [eh-stahmp].\nThis composer, who was denied a public funeral due to German bombardment in World War I, interpreted\na legend about the city of Ys [ees] in “The Sunken Cathedral” from his first book of Preludes. A Paul\nVerlaine poem inspired the third movement of his Suite bergamasque. For ten points, name this French\nImpressionist who wrote “Clair de lune.”",
        "answer": [
          "Achille-Claude Debussy",
          "Claude Debussy",
          "Debussy"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Indonesian gamelan music is played by large ensembles of this broad class of instrument. Other\nexamples of this type of instrument include the Indian tabla, claves [klah-vays] in Cuban music, and\ncastanets.",
        "answer": [
          "percussion instruments",
          "percussion"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Bricks of this color were used in the background of the mosaics on the Ishtar Gate to imitate a mineral mined near Sar-i Sang. Tin-glazed pottery of this color over white was produced by artists in 17th century Delft. This color names a period in which works like The Old Guitarist were created by a somber Pablo Picasso. For ten points, name this color that, during the Middle Ages, was produced in artworks by crushing lapis lazuli into pigments like ultramarine.",
        "answer": [
          "blue",
          "specific types of blue, such as ultramarine and lapis lazuli before mentioned BONUS:LapislazulifromtheSar-iSangmineswastradedalongtheWakhanCorridor,whichiscontrolled by this country and gives it a short border with China. ANSWER: Islamic Republic of Afghanistan 3 This event took place in its chosen city because the Justizpalast was one of the few undamaged buildings available. Alfred Jodl , Hans Frank, and Wilhelm Frick were among those convicted during this event, as was Hermann Goering, who was found hanged in his prison cell the day before his scheduled execution. For ten points, name this series of post-World War II military tribunals that convicted former Nazis of war crimes. ANSWER: Nuremberg Trials",
          "word forms and elaborations"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Deputy Fuhrer was also put on trial at Nuremberg, having fled Germany in 1941 to negotiate peace talks in Scotland. After the trials, he was imprisoned in Spandau Prison until his 1987 suicide.",
        "answer": "Rudolf Hess"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This composer reused a theme from his Gegenliebe in a piece that had to be restarted at its premiere concert, his Choral Fantasy. That concert of this man’s works also featured a five-movement symphony depicting a thunderstorm and a piece whose opening motif was used by the Allies to represent “V for Victory” in World War II. The notes G-G-G-E form the “fate knocking on the door” motif in, for ten points, what German composer’s fifth of nine symphonies?",
        "answer": "Ludwig van Beethoven"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The aforementioned 1808 concert featured Beethoven as the soloist premiering the fourth of his pieces in what genre? Beethoven wrote five in total, the last of which is nicknamed “Emperor.”",
        "answer": "piano concerto"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Joseph von Eybler and Franz Sussmayr worked to complete an unfinished work by this composer. A legend claims that a masked man, working on behalf of Franz von Walsegg, commissioned that piece from this composer, who became convinced he was writing it for his own funeral. This composer completed work on The Magic Flute a few months before his 1792 death in Vienna. For ten points, name this Austrian composer who first gained fame as a child prodigy.",
        "answer": "Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mozart was working on this type of musical work, a mass for the dead, at the time of his death.",
        "answer": "Requiem Mass"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader’s son dismissed pogroms after this leader’s death with the line “when a great tree falls, the earth shakes.” This leader used a slogan translating as “abolish poverty, rescue the country” and launched Operation Blue Star against the Golden Temple at Amritsar, leading to her assassination by her own bodyguards. After her death, this leader’s post was taken by her son, Rajiv. For ten points, name this first female Prime Minister of India.",
        "answer": "Indira Gandhi"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Operation Blue Star targeted members of this faith, who were occupying the Golden Temple at Amritsar, this religion’s holiest site. Indira Gandhi’s assassins were members of this fath.",
        "answer": "Sikhism"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A mounted archer aims at a group of naked women in the first painting by this artist accepted into the Paris Salon, Scene of War in the Middle Ages. This painter of the historical scene Young Spartans Exercising spent time in New Orleans with his brother Rene, leading to his painting of the city’s cotton exchange. Rehearsal on Stage and Fin d’Arabesque are by, for ten points, what French impressionist who frequently depicted ballet dancers?",
        "answer": "Edgar Degas"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The National Gallery houses one of Degas’s first history paintings, which shows a group of this ruler’s followers staring at him in awe. A mosaic in Pompeii’s House of the Faun depicts this ruler in a victory.",
        "answer": [
          "Alexander the Great",
          "Alexander III of Macedon"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This artist used a birds-eye view to show a road winding through a Massachusetts town in bright moonlight in his depiction of The Midnight Ride of Paul Revere. Three elderly women stand in front of a reproduction of Washington Crossing the Delaware in his painting Daughters of Revolution. This artist used his sister and his dentist as models in his painting in which a man holds a pitchfork in his right hand. For ten points, name this artist of American Gothic.",
        "answer": "Grant Wood"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "American Gothic was inspired by a farmhouse in Eldon in this U.S. state, where Grant Wood was born and raised.",
        "answer": "Iowa"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At the conclusion of one of this man’s works, a wheelchair-ridden Edgar Ray Killen appears to brag about the murders he committed as a member of the Klan; that opera alternates between the civil rights movement and the end of the Civil War and is called Appomattox. One of this man’s operas features the funeral of Amenhotep III and the “Hymn of the Sun,” and another includes a series of “knee plays.” For ten points, name this American composer whose Akhenaten is part of a trilogy with Einstein on the Beach.",
        "answer": "Philip Glass"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Akhenaten and Einstein on the Beach are parts of Glass’s Portrait trilogy, as is this work about three nonviolent activists: Leo Tolstoy, Martin Luther King, and Mahatma Gandhi.",
        "answer": "Satyagraha"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Wilhelm Furtwangler conducted this piece at the 1951 re-opening of the Bayreuth [bye-ROYT] Festival. The piece’s finale features a 6/8 Turkish March and includes a bass soloist who sings “O friends, not these tones!” Leonard Bernstein substituted the word “Freiheit” [FRY-hite] for “Freude” [froy-deh] when conducting this piece after the fall of the Berlin Wall. Friedrich Schiller’s poem “Ode to Joy” is set to music in, for ten points, what symphony, the last by Ludwig van Beethoven?",
        "answer": [
          "Symphony No. 9 in D minor by Ludwig van Beethoven [",
          "9 alone after “Beethoven” is read",
          "Choral Symphony"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This composer orchestrated an arrangement of Beethoven’s 9th Symphony for the 1872 opening of the Bayreuth Festival Theater, where this man premiered his Ring cycle four years later.",
        "answer": "Richard Wagner"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of this composer’s works was re-arranged for use as the anthem of the UEFA [you-ay-fah] Champions League; that work, Zadok the Priest, has been used for the coronation of every English king since George II. This man helped commemorate the signing of the Treaty of Aix-la-Chapelle in his Music for the Royal Fireworks. For ten points, name this composer whose oratorio Messiah includes the Hallelujah chorus.",
        "answer": "George Frederick Handel"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Handel’s Music for the Royal Fireworks was written to celebrate the Treaty of Aix-la-Chapelle and the end of this war in 1748.",
        "answer": "War of the Austrian Succession"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This Regionalist work was inspired by the artist’s visit to the town of Eldon, Iowa and titled for a style of architecture that appears in the farmhouse in the background. The central figures in this painting were modeled by the artist’s dentist and sister, who was irritated when this painting was originally exhibited as “an Iowa farmer and his wife.” For ten points, name this Grant Wood double portrait of a stoic pitchfork-holding farmer and his unamused daughter.",
        "answer": "American Gothic"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "American Gothic was awarded third prize in a competition held by this midwestern city’s Art Institute, which then purchased the painting for its collection.",
        "answer": "Art Institute of Chicago"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A piece inspired by this war begins with a tone cluster for fifty-two strings and was originally called 8 Minutes, 37 Seconds by Krzysztof Penderecki [krish-toff pen-der-etz-kee]. A cantata about an event during this war begins “I cannot remember everything” and ends with the singing of the Shema. Henryk Gorecki’s Symphony of Sorrowful Songs centers on this war and used text from the wall of a Gestapo prison cell. For ten points, name this war memorialized by “A Survivor From Warsaw.”",
        "answer": "World War II"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This composer was inspired by Hitler’s 1941 attack on Russia to write his Leningrad Symphony, which includes a famous “Invasion” theme.",
        "answer": "Dmitri Dmitriyevich Shostakovich"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A 22-bar recurring theme in this work was inspired by a song from Franz Lehar’s The Merry Widow. The Bolshoi Theatre Orchestra ended up premiering this piece in place of the intended city’s orchestra, because the musicians in the latter were either starving or fighting. Known for its “invasion” theme, this piece was supposedly dedicated to a place “that Stalin destroyed and Hitler merely finished off.” For ten points, name this Dmitri Shostakovich symphony nicknamed for a Russian city that faced a siege during World War II.",
        "answer": [
          "Leningrad Symphony",
          "Symphony Number 7, in C major, Opus 60"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Shostakovich’s Symphony No. 12, subtitled The Year of 1917, was written in honor of this man who became the head of Soviet Russia in that year.",
        "answer": [
          "Vladimir Ilyich Lenin",
          "Vladimir Ilyich Ulyanov T"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An opera about this man written on the 400th anniversary of his most famous undertaking was composed by Alberto Franchetti and premiered in the Teatro de Felice in this man's birthplace. A Paul Claudel play inspired the libretto of another opera about this man that was composed by Darius Milhaud. The second act of Philip Glass's The Voyage ends with the First Mate exclaiming that he sighted land. That act begins with this man leaving the court of his patron Queen Isabella I. For ten points, name this Italian explorer best remembered for his 1492 journey to the New World.",
        "answer": "Christopher Columbus"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The first land Columbus sighted he named San Salvador, but its native Taíno name is Guanahani. That island is part of an archipelago that comprises this modern nation of more than 700 islands that gained independence from the UK in 1973.",
        "answer": "Commonwealth of the Bahamas"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The architects of this federal building were Cass Gilbert and Cass Gilbert Jr., and it was designated aNationalHistoricalLandmarkin1987.Priortoitscompletionin1935,this building's main inhabitants worked in the Old Senate Chambers. Recent workers in this building include Elena Kagan, Neil Gorsuch, and Chief Justice John Roberts. For ten points, name this building in Washington D.C., home to the federal judicial branch.",
        "answer": "United StatesSupreme CourtBuilding accepttheMarble Palace"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This politician is the only person to have served both as U.S. president and Chief Justice and was the main proponent ofbuildingthenewSupremeCourtBuildingduringthe 1920s.",
        "answer": "William HowardTaft"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Early 20th century observers believed this building in the U.S. would collapse by itself, having become known as \"Burnham's Folly\" before construction. This building served as a hub of young publishers as the MacMillan Publishing company rented all 21 stories of this building by the mid 1950s. A contemporary reporter of the New York Tribune called this building \"A stingy piece of pie/the greatest inanimate troublemaker in New York.\" For ten points, name this triangular building which names a neighborhood in Manhattan.",
        "answer": [
          "Flatiron Building",
          "Flatiron District"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Flatiron Building was initially named for this \"Father of the Modern Skyscraper,\" whose construction company built the Lincoln Memorial and the New York Times Building.",
        "answer": "George Fuller"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "THE SOVIET UNION",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Its capital, which hosted the boycotted 1980 Summer Olympics?",
          "answer": "Moscow"
        },
        {
          "question": "the walled fortress near Red Square where Soviet leaders ruled?",
          "answer": "Kremlin"
        },
        {
          "question": "The dictator whose 1938 Great Purge ousted political dissidents?",
          "answer": [
            "Joseph Stalin",
            "Stalin",
            "Josef Vissarionovich Dzhugashvilli",
            "Dzhugashvilli"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Its intelligence agency, once led by Yuri Andropov?",
          "answer": [
            "KGB",
            "Komitet gosudarstvennoy bezopasnosti",
            "Committee for State Security"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "the Soviet defense treaty meant to counter NATO?",
          "answer": "Warsaw Pact"
        },
        {
          "question": "Its final Premier, who resigned in 1991?",
          "answer": [
            "Mikhail Gorbachev",
            "Gorbachev"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "the process of political restructuring that hastened the end of the USSR?",
          "answer": "perestroika"
        },
        {
          "question": "The agency led by Nikolai Yezhov which carried out the Great Purge?",
          "answer": [
            "NKVD",
            "Narodnyy Komissariat Vnutrennikh Del"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "In this history of the Soviet Union, who or what was..."
    },
    {
      "category": "be prompted for responding “Gandhi.” Name the...",
      "prompt": "Name the be prompted for responding “gandhi.” name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Nonviolent Indian independence leader known as Bapu, who was shot by Nathuram Godse in 1948.",
          "answer": [
            "Mohandas Gandhi",
            "Mahatma Gandhi"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "British monopoly he protested by marching to the sea at Dandi.",
          "answer": "salt march"
        },
        {
          "question": "Unrelated woman who was the first Prime Minister of India.",
          "answer": "Indira Gandhi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of now-banned test she oversaw in 1974, codenamed “Smiling Buddha.”",
          "answer": [
            "nuclear weapons test",
            "anything related to testing a nuclear/atomic bomb"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1984 military operation she authorized in Amritsar, a siege of the Golden Temple.",
          "answer": [
            "Operation Blue Star",
            "Operation Metal"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Religious background of the group attacked in that operation, as well as of her bodyguards, who assassinated her after that operation.",
          "answer": "Sikhism"
        },
        {
          "question": "Her son, who succeeded her as Prime Minister and was assassinated himself in 1991.",
          "answer": "Rajiv Gandhi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Lower house of Indian Parliament in which he served before becoming Prime Minister.",
          "answer": "Lok Sabha"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the third century AD, this building was the home of a red idol with a golden right\nhand that depicted Hubal. The construction of this building was traditionally attributed to (20 pts) ",
        "Ibrahim, who journeyed with his son Ishmael to a spot near the Well of Zamzam. This\nbuilding was cleared of idols near the start of the (10 pts) ",
        "Islamic era and is now the destination of\nthe hajj, or pilgrimage. For 10 points, name this black, square building around which Mecca is\nbuilt."
      ],
      "answer": "the Kaaba"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this larger operation, soldiers were executed at Chenogne (pr. chay-NON) in\nrevenge for the earlier Malmedy (pr. mahl-may-DEE) Massacre. Anthony McAuliffe issued\nthe singular reply (20 pts) ",
        "\"Nuts!\" to a surrender demand during this operation, which was\nnamed for the (10 pts) ",
        "shape created in a map of troop lines in the Ardennes forest. For 10 points,\nname this late 1944 World War II initiative, the final major German offensive of the war."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battle of the Bulge",
        "Bulge"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) To show that the Federal Reserve's contractionary economic policy exacerbated the\nGreat Depression, this man collaborated with Anna Schwartz on A (20 pts) ",
        "Monetary History of\nthe United States. He popularized his ideas on the relationship between the free market and\nindividual liberty in the PBS miniseries Free to Choose. (10 pts) ",
        "For 10 points, name this leader of\nthe Chicago school of economics who founded monetarism."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Milton Friedman",
        "Friedman"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Guns fired from this building ended the Battle of the Faubourg St. Antoine (pr. foo-BOO\nsont AHN-twan) during the Fronde. This building is where the Marquis de (20 pts) ",
        "Sade enraged\ncrowds by claiming a plot to massacre its inhabitants. Only seven politically unimportant (10 pts) ",
        "prisoners were found inside when it was stormed on July 14, 1789. For 10 points, name this\nParis prison which was destroyed to start the French Revolution."
      ],
      "answer": "the Bastille"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One composer from this country wrote a microtonal work for 52 strings dedicated to\na city devastated by the atomic bomb, Threnody to the Victims of Hiroshima. Another\ncomposer born here wrote etudes nicknamed “Tristesse” and (20 pts) ",
        "“Black Key.” This\ncountry’s November Uprising also inspired the Revolutionary Étude of that composer. The (10 pts) ",
        "mazurka was a popular dance in, for ten points, what Eastern European home of Krystzof Penderecki\n[KRISH-toff pen-der-ETZ-ky] that inspired the piano works of its native, Frederic Chopin [sho-PAN]?"
      ],
      "answer": "Poland"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A parrot rests on a sign in one work by this artist, in which a cat, an ox, a rabbit, and\nan elk represent the Four Humors. A demon under a rainbow holds a sign bearing the title\nof this artist’s (20 pts) ",
        "Melencolia I. This artist incorrectly added a horn to his depiction of an\nanimal that had been given to Lisbon by Indian diplomats in 1515, and showed (10 pts) ",
        "Famine,\nWar, Plague, and Death trampling peasants in another work. For ten points, name this German creator\nof woodcuts like the Four Horsemen of the Apocalypse and Rhinoceros."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Albrecht Durer",
        "Durer"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) In response to this event, Mossad launched Operation Wrath of God and\nOperation Spring of Youth. This event’s perpetrators demanded the release of\nAndreas Baader and (20 pts) ",
        "Ulrike Meinhoff, the founders of the Red Army Faction, (10 pts) ",
        "Haganah. For ten points, name this event that saw members of Black September kill 11 Israeli\ncoaches and athletes at the 1972 Summer Olympics in a certain German city."
      ],
      "answer": "Munich Massacre"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This artist began his career with historical images like The Misfortunes of the City of\nOrleans, and painted his aunt with her daughters and husband, Baron Gennaro (20 pts) ",
        "Bellelli.\nHis first work to be bought by a museum shows his uncle, Michel Musson’s, title Cotton\nOffice in New Orleans. A man wearing a black hat and a woman in a white dress sit in a\ncafe with a glass of the title (10 pts) ",
        "green beverage in this artist’s L’Absinthe. For ten points, name this\nFrench artist who painted many depictions of young ballerinas."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Edgar Degas",
        "Degas"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This painting is a companion to The Charge of the Mamelukes. It includes a cubic\nlantern that illuminates the pile of bodies below the group on the left. In this work, a (20 pts) ",
        "monk huddles near a man in white and yellow, who stands with his arms stretched upwards\nin (10 pts) ",
        "surrender. For ten points, name this painting in which a shadowy Napoleonic firing squad takes\naim at Spanish citizens in Madrid, a painting by Francisco Goya."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "The Third of May 1808: The Execution of the Defenders of Madrid",
        "The Third of May 1808",
        "El tres de mayo de 1808 en Madrid",
        "El tres de mayo de 1808",
        "Los fusilamientos de la montana del Principe Pio",
        "Los fusilamientos del tres de mayo"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This city is home to the tomb of Ulysses S. Grant. An International style building in\nthis city designed by Ludwig Mies van der Rohe has a bronze and glass fa¸cade. This home\ncity of the (20 pts) ",
        "Seagram building includes a large park designed by Frederick Law Olmsted.\nOne building in this city has corner decorations modeled after (10 pts) ",
        "radiator caps, and a large\nart deco style “crown.” For ten points, name this city whose skyscrapers include the Chrysler Building\nand Empire State Building."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "New York City",
        "New York",
        "NYC",
        "Manhattan"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This figure is shown wearing a prayer shawl around his waist in the center of a Marc\nChagall work showing Jews fleeing a pogrom. James Ensor painted this figure’s theoretical\nentry into (20 pts) ",
        "Brussels. Paul Gauguin showed this figure alongside three Breton women in\na painting that emphasizes the color (10 pts) ",
        "yellow. Artistic scenes including this figure after his death\ninclude Deposition and Pieta, in which he is held by his mourning mother, Mary. For ten points, name\nthis religious figure painted in scenes of the Crucifixion."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Jesus Christ",
        "Jesus",
        "Christ"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One opera set in this country includes an offstage chorus singing Psalm 104 and is the\nfinal entry in the “Portrait Trilogy.” Another opera set in this country was commissioned\nby Ismail Pasha to celebrate the opening of the Khedival Opera House and features the\ntitle princess singing (20 pts) ",
        "“O patria mia.” This country is the setting of a Philip Glass\nopera about a pioneering monotheistic ruler and a Verdi opera in which the title princess is\nburied alive with (10 pts) ",
        "Radames. For ten points, name this ancient civilization, the setting of Aida and\nAkhnaten."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Egypt",
        "ancient Egypt"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This composer’s Adagio and Rondo was written for an ensemble that included Benjamin\nFranklin’s glass armonica. His final three string quartets were written for Friedrich Wilhelm\nII of (20 pts) ",
        "Prussia, and his eleventh piano sonata ends with an imitation of Janissary bands\nfrom the Ottoman Empire. The impresario Johann Peter Salomon gave this man’s forty-first\nand (10 pts) ",
        "final symphony the nickname Jupiter. K¨ochel [ker-kel] numbers are used to catalogue the works\nof, for ten points, what composer of the “Rondo alla Turca” and Eine Kleine Nachtmusik?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart",
        "Mozart"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Boston police threatened this person with a $100 fine for using a dominant seventh\nchord in his arrangement of The Star-Spangled Banner. Allied victory in World War II\ninspired the coda of this composer’s Symphony in Three Movements, and a dissonant chord\nrepresents the title (20 pts) ",
        "puppet in a ballet he wrote for Serge Diaghilev’s Ballet Russes.\nAnother piece by this composer of Petrushka, in which a young girl dances herself to death\nin a sacrificial rite, (10 pts) ",
        "caused a riot at its 1913 premiere. For ten points, name this Russian composer\nof the Rite of Spring."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Igor Fyodorovich Stravinsky",
        "Stravinsky"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This general went around the Gazala Line to defeat Claude Auchinleck and stopped\nOperation Battleaxe. He commanded Army Group B in defense of Northern Italy and\ndesigned the Atlantic (20 pts) ",
        "Wall. A tank division he commanded was nicknamed the “Ghost”\nDivision for moving to fast to be tracked. He launched several offensives aimed at (10 pts) ",
        "Cairo,\nbut was defeated by Bernard Montgomery at the Battle of El Alamein. For ten points, name this Nazi\nGerman commander of the North African campaign, nicknamed the “Desert Fox.”"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Erwin Rommel",
        "Rommel"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This musician included “Feux Follets” [foh follay] and a piece inspired by hetman\nIvan Mazeppa in a series of twelve hard piano pieces. This composer’s orchestral piece\nLes pr´eludes was the first “symphonic poem,” and his illegitimate daughter (20 pts) ",
        "Cosima\nmarried Richard Wagner [ree-kard vahg-ner]. He used Roma melodies for a set of nineteen\npiano showpieces named for his home (10 pts) ",
        "country. For ten points, name this Romantic composer of\nthe Transcendental Etudes and Hungarian Rhapsodies who inspired a namesake “mania” in 19th century\nFrance."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Franz Liszt",
        "Liszt",
        "Liszt Ferenc"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This emperor designed a building that looked like a palace, but was a torture chamber\nwhose name translated to “Hell-On-Earth.” This “Beloved-of-the-Gods” put down a minor\nrevolt in his empire at Taxila, and he ruled his kingdom from (20 pts) ",
        "Maghda. This ruler’s\nsculpture of four-outward facing lions at Sarnath and his 24-spoked “wheel of righteousness”\nwere designed after he waged a bloody war in (10 pts) ",
        "Kalinga, after which he converted to Buddhism.\nFor ten points, name this descendant of Chandragupta, a ruler of the Mauryan Empire."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Ashoka the Great",
        "Ashoka Maurya",
        "Ashoka",
        "Ashok",
        "Asoka"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Sergeant Leon Weckstein claimed to have spared this building from destruction during\nWorld War II. This building, located in the Square of Miracles, is thought to have been\nconstructed by Diotisalvi. (20 pts) ",
        "Mussolini ordered the drilling of 100 holes into this structure\nas an attempt at fixing it. According to legend, this building was used to disprove an (10 pts) ",
        "Aristotelian theory about spheres of different masses. For ten points, name this Italian structure whose\nweak foundation gives it a famous four-degree tilt."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Leaning Tower of Pisa",
        "Tower of Pisa"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Contrary to popular legend about this composer, audiences actually requested “Immenso Jehova” as an encore, though mourners at this man’s funeral did break out into “Va, pensiero.” That song, the chorus of the (20 pts)",
        "Hebrew slaves from this composer’s Nabucco, became an anthem of the (10 pts)",
        "Risorgimento, during which this man’s name was used as an acronym in support of King Victor Emmanuel. For ten points, name this 19th-century Italian composer also known for the operas La Traviata and Aida."
      ],
      "answer": "Giuseppe Verdi"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man wears a crown of laurels on his deathbed in a Horace Vernet painting, and he holds a gold orb in a statue by Antonio Canova that portrays him as (20 pts)",
        "“Mars the Peacemaker.” This man touches the wound of a shirtless soldier in a painting by Antoine Jean-Gros set in a plague house at (10 pts)",
        "Jaffa. In another painting, Pope Pius VII blesses this ruler as he crowns his wife, Josephine. For ten points, name this emperor who crosses the Alps on a rearing horse in an 1801 painting by Jacques-Louis David [dah-veed]."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Napoleon I Bonaparte",
        "either underlined part"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This composer wrote a Dervish chorus and a Turkish march for The Ruins of Athens, a selection of music to accompany a play written by German diplomat August von Kotzebue. The first opera played in post-war Berlin was a 1945 performance of this composer’s only opera, (20 pts)",
        "Fidelio. In 1989 at the Berlin Wall, Leonard Bernstein directed a modified version of this composer’s (10 pts)",
        "Choral Symphony. For ten points, name this German composer who used the “Ode to Joy” in his ninth and final symphony."
      ],
      "answer": "Ludwig van Beethoven"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After his patron refused to pay him for one work, this artist painted Frederick Leyland as an anthropomorphic bird playing a piano. This artist of The Gold Scab was bankrupted when he received just a quarter-penny in an 1877 libel suit against John (20 pts)",
        "Ruskin, who claimed he was “flinging a pot of paint in the public’s face” with his (10 pts)",
        "Nocturne in Black and Gold: The Falling Rocket. A seated woman in a black dress is the subject of an “Arrangement” by, for ten points, what artist, who had his mother sit for the painting?"
      ],
      "answer": "James Abbott McNeill Whistler"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Alfred Einstein was the foremost 20th century biographer of this composer, whose 26th piano concerto was played at the coronation of Leopold II. This composer’s works are collected in the (20 pts)",
        "K¨ochel catalog, whose final numbered entry is his Requiem. As a child, this (10 pts)",
        "prodigy toured Europe with his sister Nannerl and father Leopold. For ten points, name this composer of the Jupiter symphony and operas like The Marriage of Figaro and The Magic Flute."
      ],
      "answer": "Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) To promote the London Underground, Horace Taylor created a poster of commuters on escalators in this artistic style. Hidden bars with mirror-topped tables were created in this style to conceal liquor during Prohibition. A street named for Benjamin Franklin is home to one of the earliest (20 pts)",
        "buildings in this style created by Henri Sauvage in Paris. Another building designed in this style was decorated with radiator caps and gargoyles and, upon completion in (10 pts)",
        "1931, surpassed the Empire State Building as the tallest building in the world. The Chrysler Building exemplifies, for ten points, what highly modern style that flourished in the 1920s?"
      ],
      "answer": "Art Deco"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This artist, who painted a yellow bedframe in his blue Bedroom at Arles, failed to sell most of his still-lives of roses, irises and sunflowers during his lifetime. Self-portraits with a straw hat and (20 pts)",
        "bandage were painted by this man, whose most famous work was created while institutionalized in Saint-R´emy. Cypress (10 pts)",
        "trees rise up into a swirled blue and yellow evening sky in a work by, for ten points, what Dutch artist of The Starry Night who famously cut off his own ear?"
      ],
      "answer": "Vincent Willem van Gogh"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This composer wrote a theme and variations for piano and orchestra on Mozart’s aria “L`a ci darem la mano.” This composer wrote a piano piece in response to the revolutions of 1848 that was nicknamed (20 pts)",
        "“Heroic” by his lover, George Sand. This composer’s personal response to the 1831 November Uprising was his (10 pts)",
        "E´tude on the Bombardment of Warsaw. For ten points, name this foremost composer of mazurkas, the Polish-born composer of the Minute Waltz and Revolutionary E´tude."
      ],
      "answer": "Fr´ed´eric Fran¸cois Chopin"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man never premiered his works in Paris again after the Jockey Club used a performance of his Tannhauser [TAHN-hoyz-er] to stage a demonstration against Napoleon III. This man's music was criticized as pandering to extremists in the Untimely Meditations of Friedrich (20 pts)",
        "Nietzsche, which includes an essay about this man in Bayreuth [BYE-roit]. This man's debt was settled by Ludwig II of Bavaria, under whose patronage he premiered (10 pts)",
        "Tristan und Isolde. For ten points, name this notedly anti-Semitic composer of the Ring Cycle."
      ],
      "answer": "Richard Wagner"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This artist's The Lictors Bring to Brutus the Bodies of His Sons was painted to symbolize the ideas of sacrificing for the greater good and equality before the law. This artist's depiction of a story from Plato's (20 pts)",
        "Phaedo is on loan to MOMA, and he depicted an emperor he admired greatly in Napoleon (10 pts)",
        "Crossing the Alps. For ten points, name this influential French Neoclassical painter, known for The Death of Socrates and The Death of Marat."
      ],
      "answer": "Jacques-Louis David"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Alex Kershaw’s book The Bedford Boys chronicled the story of Company A of the 116th Infantry, which suffered heavy losses during this battle. Operation Fortitude South sought to convince the defenders that George Patton’s First United States Army Group would target (20 pts)",
        "Pas-de-Calais instead of the objective of this operation. James Rudder’s Army Rangers suffered heavy losses while storming the (10 pts)",
        "cliffs of Pointe-du-Hoc during this battle. Five beachheads were established at Sword, Gold, Juno, Utah, and Omaha during this battle. For ten points, name this June 6, 1944 Allied invasion of Normandy."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "D-Day",
        "Operation Overlord,",
        "Battle of Normandy before it is mentioned R"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This painting was hidden after a failed student uprising, the June Rebellion, led to it being seen as incendiary. This painting is set during the “Three Glorious Days” during which the (20 pts)",
        "July Monarchy was established. This painting’s primary subject wears a symbolic Phrygian cap and is flanked by a university student wearing a bicorne. The Notre F Dame in this painting’s background notably features a flying flag, apart from the (10 pts)",
        "tricolour that Marianne holds. For ten points, name this Eug`ene Delacroix painting showing the personification of freedom at the forefront of revolution."
      ],
      "answer": "Liberty Leading the People"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "One composer from this modern-day country used a \"sacred minimalist\" sound that is exemplified by his Symphony of Sorrowful Songs and the (*) Copernican Symphony. Another composer from this country wrote a series of pieces based on music from this country, including mazurkas and polonaises, though he is best known for his études and the Minute Waltz. (*) For ten points, name this home country of Henryk Górecki and Frédéric Chopin [[shoh-PAHN]], who was born in the Duchy of Warsaw."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Republic of Poland or Rzeczpospolita Polska",
        "Polish",
        "Second Polish Republic"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A 1980 film made about this caseisentitled[itsplaintiff's]Trumpet.Thiscase selectively incorporated the Sixth (20 pts)",
        "Amendment across the United States. The plaintiff in this case, who hadrobbedaFloridapoolhall,wasnotgrantedcounseldue to having only committed a felony, as opposed to a capital (10 pts)",
        "offense. For ten points, name this 1963 Supreme Court decision that established the legal right to counsel for defendants who are unable to afford their own attorneys. ANSWER:Gideonv. Wainwright(orClarence E.Gideonv. Louie L. Wainwright, Corrections Director) (2) A boldly polyphonic opera named for this character was originallyperformed at the 1607 Carnival for the court in Mantua and istheearlieststill-performedopera of Monteverdi. (+) A lampoon of this character's story by Jacques Offenbach [[OH-fen-bahk]] includes the \"Galop Infernal,\" a song later adapted to the can-can dance, and is titled for [this character] in the Underworld. (*) For ten points,namethis musically-gifted Greek hero, whose love for Eurydice [[yoo-RIH-dih-see]] is the subject of many operas. ANSWER:Orpheus[[OHR-fee-us]] (acceptL'Orfeo; acceptOrpheusin the Underworld) (3) While serving under this man, a young P. G. T. Beauregard provided vital reconnaissance during the Battle of Cerro Gordo. Shortly before his death, this man formulated the Anaconda (+) Plan as a way to cut-off the Confederacy from naval trade. The amphibious seizure of Veracruz by this man facilitated his march on Mexico (*) City during the Mexican-AmericanWar.Fortenpoints,namethisone-timeWhig presidential candidate and general known as \"Old Fuss 'n' Feathers.\""
      ],
      "answer": "WinfieldScott"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While under the engineer Lucius Cornelius Balbus, this man led the artillery corps during Caesar's Gallic campaign. This man innovated the technology of the hypocaust[[HY-poh-kost]],whichprovidedcentral (20 pts)",
        "heatingtovillasandbaths.This polymath stated that all buildings should have \"Utility, Strength, and Beauty\" in his multi-volume workDeArchitectura[[ar-kee-tek-TOO-rah]].Leonardo (10 pts)",
        "DaVincidrew a figure of a \"Man\" named for, for ten points, which ancient Roman architect?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "MarcusVitruviusPollio",
        "theVitruvianMan 2021-22 C Set History"
      ]
    }
  ]
}